okay hello
everyone welcome to the active inference
lab
to an active inference live stream with
john boyk
this is going to be great it's our
second
of these interactive discussions on the
sequence of papers
that john has written and today
we're gonna be hearing about motivation
and strategy as well as active inference
of course
a lot so i'm daniel friedman i'm a
postdoc in california
and i'm gonna pass it to john to
introduce myself
lead us into this second discussion
while i share the jamboard link with our
live participants
so john thanks again for coming on and
please take it away
all right daniel thanks for having me on
again this is great
um all right so my name is john boyk uh
i'm a
courtesy faculty at oregon state
university environmental sciences
graduate program
and uh we're here in this series of
talks this is the second in the series
to
talk about the the um series of three
papers that i recently published
in the journal sustainability the topic
is societal transformation
in particular the de novo development of
new societal systems new economic
systems new governance systems legal
systems educational systems and so on
and last week as maybe you can see on
the jamboard now
last week we started with the first part
which was on world worldview the topic
the title is science-driven
societal transformation part one
worldview and
uh we didn't actually get through that
so we're going to pick up a few
tail end ideas there and then hopefully
start on the second paper part two
which is uh subtitled motivation and
strategy
and the links for the three papers are
there and i of course
encourage people to download the papers
they're
they're open access so everyone can get
them for
free um page two
perhaps yep
okay uh so uh just for more information
about the the project about the for the
links for the papers for other links
there's a
bunch of uh little articles that you
could look at if you're interested
there's also an interactive model
you could go to the principled societies
project
website and the address is given there
so
further information if you need it you
can find it there
cool three all right three
okay all right so we uh we
didn't get through the first uh through
the paper all the way in the
in the first our first talk so there's a
few things that i'd like to catch up on
uh before we move on to
paper part two um we we touched on
active inference
uh in the in the lat in our last talk
but we didn't really get around to
discussing it so i want to say a few
words about active inference itself
a little bit of a description about it
for those who are not familiar
um and then we have the topics of
cooperation and communication
and uh the the concept that complex
organisms have complex needs
and then on to some practical
implications and this is
really the main thing i wanted to finish
up with is that
in in part one i i provide some kind of
high level sort of
[Music]
abstract concepts and i would imagine
that the reader in certain places might
be wondering
why are we discussing this what does
this have to do with
actually building new societal systems
so i want to talk about
a little bit of the practical
implications of all of this
kind of abstract all these abstract
notions that we've been working with
so i would like to just
recall just a few ideas from our last
talk uh and one is the and that
i i claim at least that is society has
an intrinsic purpose
and uh that and and by intrinsic purpose
i really mean
a biological purpose that we have gained
through
eons of evolution and that intrinsic
purpose
is the same purpose that every living
organism has
so every living organism has this
purpose whether that's a
bacteria or a human and then i also
claim that society is an organism
that can be seen as an organism can be
viewed as an organism
and a society has the same intrinsic
purpose so
if we're if our task is to develop new
societal systems it really
helps to have some ideas of well who are
we and who are we building this for
and what is the purpose of uh if we were
to build a new
societal system new economic system for
example
what what would be the purpose and
if we know the purpose then we can take
the remaining
the next step and say okay we know what
an economic system is supposed to do we
know what a government system is
supposed to do
so is this new design design a design
bead
is it fit for purpose that's where
that's the
concept is that if we're going to
design new societal systems de novo from
scratch
then we ought to have an idea of what
they are supposed to do
and then how we might measure their
fitness so that we can determine
did we did we create something that is
fit for purpose and which one of these
options which one of these designs might
be more fit for purpose
than others all right so that's that's
kind of where we're going here
and uh so the the i claim that the
intrinsic purpose of a society and
organism any organism or any organism
is to achieve and maintain vitality
which is accomplished through
largely through cognition and
cooperation
and so to maintain and achieve vitality
for who and that who i claim is the
extended self
so the extent this all of us
are are enmeshed
in our world enmeshed in our environment
enmeshed in
in a society with each other and
if we're speaking of a body then the
extended self
is those interactions
with those necessary and vital
interactions with
the rest of the world so the extended
self then is the self
that extends to other people to to
societies to other societies to the
environment the local environment the
global environment the biosphere
so then in that sense then if our
purpose is to
achieve and maintain fit vitality our
achieve achieve and maintain vitality
for that
larger extended self that really
goes all the way to the biosphere where
all of life
is in this together all of life is
connected in one
and uh and all of life is doing this
thing
doing this thing of acting to achieve
and maintain vitality
and over eons of evolution we get this
amazing
world of life and whales and sequoia
trees and
ecosystems and all these tea trees
talking to a fungi in the ground
and plants talking to each other and
beads doing their thing with
flowers and each other and i mean it's
just like
amazing coordination
and communication and cooperation
happening between species and within a
species and within a
human body like all of our cells
so we just if i would say that if we're
going to
create a better society or create new
systems that lead to a better society
then the task will be to to fulfill our
intrinsic purpose
which in in a way means to simply get
with the program
that is get with the program of what all
of life is doing
around us right just align with
what life is doing and uh then we will
you know we'd be off to a good start if
we can do that
all right so that's uh that's the
purpose and then i
at the bottom of that slide i just i
highlight the word wisdom because
it is reasonable you know we we think of
a wise action is something that is
benefit you know widely beneficial
and action that is
aware of the needs of others and is
as useful action but that is what we're
talking about we're talking about
uh of of taking actions that help to
fulfill our intrinsic purpose and really
by definition i would say
that would be wise actions so in that
sense
we're aiming at a wisdom society
a society where wisdom is valued
and discussed and sought after
and you know and and hopefully one in
which
uh individuals and groups and
others institutions that act
with wisdom will be recognized you know
as such
okay so i do ask the question there at
the bottom can wisdom be reversely
defined now
often it's you know it's it's a term
that is just
generically applied to like to uh
to uh you know actions that are that are
some people feel are useful or
appear to be useful but but if we're
going to build
new societal systems and we're going to
have some sense of
fitness for these systems and the
systems are in some
way supposed to help us to act with
wisdom
and to facilitate action with wisdom
then perhaps there is some way actually
to
rigorously define wisdom or to know when
when actions are wise and i would say
then that leads us right into the
concept of active inference
because because uh through active
inference we what we might say that
actions that reduce uncertainty and
maintain
uh you know reduce expected uncertainty
about our
are thriving or survival or survival
into the future
those are though those are benef those
are beneficial actions
and then again by definition they're
wise actions so
there might be some way to actually talk
about
wisdom in the same sentence as fitness
right the the two cons two concepts
concepts
must be closely related
okay john can i ask i have uh two things
i
wrote down so one was cognition
and when we talk about multi-scale
cognition especially with a
computational or a modeling bent it's
easy to get caught up with cognition
being a really mechanical process
but i liked how you brought it to wisdom
and so it's like if we're gonna be a
cognitive
system or if that's a framework we're
taking are we gonna be calculators
and just do zero through nine
calculations or will there be wisdom
in the system and that kind of brings me
to the question which is
clarifying wisdom is is a big
opportunity
but also there are risks and
uncertainties so
here you know in 2021 looking forward
potentially to some type of
wisdom transformation what can we
cling to and how can we follow wisdom
because it sounds like a great idea but
then how will we know it in the midst
right right okay so uh your i'll talk to
your first point
uh first that excellent so so i i want
to
emphasize that we're not talking about
building a society of
robotic you know
linear thinking logical
organisms you know that's not really
what humans are
anyway that's what no organisms are you
know we
every organism has uh
you know some degree of complexity of of
its
of itself and uh humans are very complex
it will talk about the complexity of
human needs in a moment but
this it's life is not all about logic
and uh it is partly about uh you know a
good share of it is about heart
and intuition and all the other
emotion and all the other aspects that
come to play
in in what it means to be human so i'll
repeat something i had said earlier too
is uh you know the if we are to build
better societal systems better societies
those would be societies that would help
us be ourselves more
help us be true to ourselves more true
to our hearts more true to our
deepest longings more so i'm certainly
not talking about
uh building a society of legislation
people doing logic or computational
logic or something like that that's not
at all what this is about
this is about being more human more
ourselves
more capable of of uh
making wise decisions right yep and
and i think some of these ideas from the
you know from over that that have been
developed say in the last 10 years of
science
ideas from complex systems science ideas
from cognitive science
ideas from active inference ideas from
evolutionary biology and some others
are we're in a much better position
today
to be talking about you know how how
might we do this how might we build
systems that actually recognize the full
human the full society the full the full
interactions and then
and then help provide guidance of of how
how that might best be done right yeah
just one quick point on that is
people have talked about general systems
theory and about how we could simulate
or
choose utilitarian outcomes or all these
different ideas that have been
percolating for truly thousands of years
in many cultures what's different well
in your pocket
there's something that can simulate not
the universe but it can do
calculations that complement human
abilities in a really potentially
beneficial way
that's different it's on a continuum
with other extended cognitive
elements like books and communications
telecommunications media and things like
that but we're in a computational
and a conceptual phase that's totally
novel
and so we need to consider um classical
critiques like
it can't be done it won't be done amidst
the
truly ongoing changes that's right
actually
exponentially uh expanding
capacities for computation but your
point is very well taken this
again i do not mean that we're going to
have computers
deciding our every action it's not at
all what i'm talking about i'm talking
about becoming more human and using the
tools that we have available to extend
our computation and help us to
understand
better with the you know the
complexities of the world around us
right so uh right so this is this is uh
humans taking advantage of all the tools
they have to become
more themselves and better and wiser and
and
better decision making better decision
makers
okay so uh then so that's what that's
what we're gonna cover
today uh this first part and then we'll
move on to part two
all right next slide all right four four
so um so this is a slide on uh active
inference and i just want to put
again for those who maybe are not too
familiar with the concept i want to give
a
kind of a brief overview um excellent
uh carl friskin obviously is
one of the you know the main forces
behind
this concept he's been working on it for
well over a decade now
uh uh there's a little image there on
the left of the slide that i'll just
say a few words about so we can talk
about
two uh components to the universe
uh the universe at large and then
some individual that is in some sense
separate from the universe
right so uh the the
concept of an individual is something
that is that can be demarcated from the
rest of its background so for the moment
we'll say there's
we're going to draw a circle around the
individual and then the rest of the
world is going to be
outside that circle so the rest of the
universe has
hidden states it has a you could say it
has kind of a
in a sense a generative model of how it
works how it functions
uh when it is when it has
you know is is is acted upon by an
individual it responds in some way it
has in a sense it has a model to do that
and the individual has a model of what
the individual
how it understands the larger picture
now obviously the universe
is bigger than a human mind so there is
no way that a human
mind is ever going to understand every
little detail about the universe that's
impossible so um a human then or any
really any individual is faced with this
problem of
trying to act in a universe that is far
more complex far more complicated and
and
dangerous at times so how do you how do
you act
under uncertainty that's the problem of
humans and other organisms how do you
make good decisions under uncertainty
and that's certainly the problem for
society too how do you make good
decisions wise decisions
under uncertainty so
a uh when we talk about separating the
individual from the rest of the universe
we're talking statistically we're
talking about independence from the rest
of the universe
and in this line of thinking that
independence is granted by what's called
a markov blanket
so the individual knows its
own beliefs or it has its own beliefs
and
it can choose actions and it can receive
sensations from the world so it can act
and it can observe
the the result of its actions
and then the universe on the other half
the universe is impacted by actions and
then
changes in some way has some dynamics
and then that leads to sensations
for the individual and then the
individual receives a sensation so we
have kind of a circular
pattern going on here where the uh the
individual acts
well maybe we'll say this way the
individual receives sensations
after some action receive sensations
from the universe
and then it can do really one of two
things it can
it can it can alter its beliefs about
the world maybe
maybe the sensations tell the individual
that it was wrong in some ways so maybe
one option then is for the the
individual to
update its beliefs about the world
that's uh new here
or it can take some kind of action to
better fit the work better fit his
experience
to to how it understands the world so if
i'm
cold if my sensation is being pulled my
action might be to put on a coat so that
i
don't freeze to death right i can bring
the world
a like try to align the world with what
i expect the world to
to what i expect of myself and what i
expect of my own condition
and how i expect the world to act so
that's the
that's the kind of the two options we
have available we can update our
understanding and beliefs about the
world
and we can choose actions uh so that's
really the
gist of what that picture is and then
over on the left
on the right hand side i have a few
equations that sort of puts that into
kind of a
formulative
[Music]
way so the first one that was just
that's that's as
just a slide taken from wikipedia but
the concept is that
because i'm an individual and because i
don't
i can't actually know what the
generative process of the universe is
i can only know my sensations and and
and my actions
i would like to reduce
the surprise that appears
like i don't you know it's surprising to
me if i'm cold and sick and hungry
and harmed right i don't want those
kinds of surprises
i want some certainty about me existing
into the future but the trouble is
i don't know what the world's model is
so
i have to essentially create my own
version of it
that's the the density q
in this model i'm going to create a
my best guess as to how the universe
works
and uh the universe has the density
p in this equation
and uh i'm going to do something
actually that is it's not
really common in data science so if
any data scientists are listening there
you ought to be probably
very familiar with these concepts
already this is a
variational inference so it's a
technique widely used in data science to
solve problems and it and the id that's
the central idea is
you you have some complicated density p
and you don't really know how to deal
with it so
you do you instead choose a much simpler
density q that is more better behaved
and then you work with that and the and
the whole idea is if
if if you bring q closer and closer
to p then you'll be closer and closer to
actually having a
model of the real model of the world so
uh just in that term for the elbow the
evidence lower bound is it's called in
data science
there's a kl terminal divergence term
and that just simply means that term
will go to zero
as p and q come closer
and the other term there uh log log
p uh that is really
just the negative that is called
surprise
so uh um you
the agent i would like to reduce the
surprise that it it it uh
recognizes experiences
and uh and doing and one way to do that
is to
uh is to also bring
the the densities p and q closer so you
get a good model of the universe
and you act and act in a in a way that
is consistent with your understanding of
the universe
and you update your beliefs as necessary
to be have a better model of the
universe
and if you do all of that the your
surprise
about how the universe acts and you're
surprised about
maintaining yourself into the future
will be will be reduced
so uh that's that that functional is
called a free energy
functional and the whole concept is an
active inference is to use this
action updating uh observing from the
universe what the sensations are
and then going in a circle and and
updating an action
and updating an action of you know
updating action
observation updating action observation
so
uh the the the
the idea is to reduce this functional of
free energy
and that fristen
i would say claims that
this is what all organisms are doing
this is what life is doing
and if this doing so leads to
really all the structural diversity that
we
that we are aware of in our universe the
ecologies and ecosystems and organisms
and cooperating cells within a human
body
and all of that is is is
uh has has has become what it
has become through a process
through this free energy minimization
process
so uh so in a sense if we wanted to
somehow uh
talk rigorously about wisdom it would be
in some sense
at least you know from this perspective
it would be
wise actions and and
learning activities and explorations
wisdom is
the kind of equivalent to reducing
expected free energy i just want to make
a just a few
other comments here is this
this is the simple this page is the
simple version so
uh what we really want to do is is
reduce expected free energy like
what will happen you know a tiger is
running at me
i could run i could fight
i could jump on a car i could jump in a
car
i could do all these things i have these
options paths
these paths i could take these decisions
i could take
which of them is going to be best for me
in the long run
or in the short run and so that
requires expectations of free energy
over possible
decisions of the in the future and that
becomes quite complicated
none of that is really in this slide but
i do want do you want
to everyone to realize that that's there
john i want to lock in
two really key points that you touched
on here and then ask a question
so the first is the first thing you said
on this slide is
active inference is about the reduction
of uncertainty so
that's in direct contrast with the
human as an economic maximizer or an
optimizer of the reward or that we're
trying to do some sort of
optimization maximization on an outcome
it's a process-based reduction of
uncertainty that active inference
highlights
and so of course you're highlighting the
outcomes that we want to see those are
our values our preferences
and our predictions we hope but we're
going about it with a process
based and uncertainty reduction based
lens
rather than simply like number is going
to go up
we got to get there so that's the
richness
of just if nothing else all the
critiques of active immigrants aside
to focus on the process and the
reduction of uncertainty is really
powerful
and the second lock in is you
immediately went from the reduction of
uncertainty
to collective behavior and it's like
there's things that the brain knows that
a neuron
doesn't like how to speak english and
there's things the colony
knows and does that the ant nest mate
doesn't so part of this
is about realizing well there's things
surely society knows
with all of our diversity and all of our
different skills
that an individual doesn't so what does
it look like to take that seriously
that the cognitive systems are not just
nested internally like
well the brain the brain region the
neural circuit the neuron the organelle
yeah you can go down but you can go out
and it's not just a cope and so what
that looks like is a really
important point so the two things there
reduction of uncertainty with active
inference
and multi-scale cognitive systems and
it's really
important points um good or can i ask
the question
no excellent excellent yeah go ahead i'm
just trying to catch up because
you say a lot of awesome points in each
of these
breakdowns and the question is really um
what kinds this is on the jamboard
what kinds of social processes or data
are promising
for active inference modeling let's just
say now
maybe in the future we'll license other
deployments
but right now like what kind of data
would you be curious to
collect or find out about we may talk
about it
later in the economic or social context
but what kind of data types are we
thinking about
making active inference models of
yeah okay so to answer that question
um uh i'm i'm going to ask that question
in about two more slides so i'm going to
ask that very question
to you and to the viewers out there
but i'll do i can give you just one
that's simple okay we can come back to
it but
go for an example yeah i'll just i'll
give one example uh because i also want
to emphasize something else that you
also just very briefly touched on so uh
and
also i had touched on but i want to
emphasize that if we're talking about
expected uncertainty
that implies that we
are anticipatory so i just want to
underline
that every organism is anticipatory
every organism is doing
this reducing free energy you know i
mean from this view
and that requires anticipation of
what the future will be and
so so anticipation
or you might call it forecasting
forecasting
is central to um
our our well-being our our continued
existence i'm forecasting that if i see
a tiger coming towards me
that it's i'm gonna be it's lunch if i
don't do something
so uh you know that's i if we don't
we don't think clearly about what's to
happen next
then cognition is there is no hardly any
cognition
just one one short comment on that is
anticipation
and anticipatory systems has been
discussed in many other
contexts like cybernetics and active
inference helps us walk
from this very simple beginning you said
okay there's an inside and outside
if you don't have that you know you need
to think a little bit more clearly about
the system or something like that but
we can start with the simplest and then
we can build it out to the sophisticated
affect of inference with the affective
charge and all these other
modern models but we're starting with
this
loop which is why we always come back to
these kinds of figures and why it's
really important that you're making it
at this level right
good uh so uh just so so we can ask the
question
uh all right
you know tell me like
kinds of things what does this want to
be good at forecasting
uh and you know actually i'll ask this
question a few slides so we don't have
to go too far into it now but
let's just just just take say governance
uh or leaders political leaders if
they if a political leader unders is
good at
understanding what's coming next what
the future is going to be then great
then the political leader can say hey we
better do something because
if we don't this thing is going to
happen right
but as a society today do we actually
remember
those predictions do we in any way like
you know score accuracy of people's
predictions or the predictions of
science or the predictions of
organizations is there
like how does society today remember
remember that predictions have been made
and now the future is has evolved and
come about
and how who was good at who was going to
anticipate in the future
who who excels what
what what what organization or political
group or
whatever who's been really good at
understanding what's going to come next
right
so that's just i'll just leave that an
open question
because that you know it gets the mind
working out that you can think of all
kinds of
ways that we don't do a good job of
of remembering and anticipating today
just to ask a question from the chat um
someone wrote does john use active
inference
mathematical framework in his work for
merely descriptive purposes
so potentially as opposed to generative
or like real-time decision making so
where does where are you right now or
where do you want to be with
respect to using active inference to
describe simulate
make decision support etc right right
yeah
a good question so and maybe
maybe the part of the answer to that
question is to is to tell you what stage
this project is at
so the the series has just been
published
this uh the series proposes a
r d program uh that we that
that we that society could undertake and
uh
it is conceptual at the moment uh the
the whole program is conceptual it's not
been funded it's it's
i mean you're in a sense you're looking
at it this is it
it's the three papers and our
conversation and
whatever you know other people have to
add to this
so uh this is where we're at we're we're
obviously
focusing or i'm focusing now on the the
kind of the
the big picture conceptual ideas because
that has to
it's that has to happen before you
actually get into the nuts and bolts of
okay how do we use this what how does
this go what kind of models can we build
but uh i would guess and i would expect
that if this project moves forward
then at some point we'll be talking
about the
numerous ways that the society uses
information
and how it remembers and how it
anticipates and
what models might be used for different
kinds of intuition participation
and um and you know
how do the nuts and bolts of that go
together so that's to come
that's the research project to come
and i hope i hope we get a chance to go
there that would be fantastic
we'll lay it out as likely and then
we'll make it happen okay there we go
there we go
all right so uh so that's that slides go
on to the next
sounds good five yeah and and maybe
two you know before we move off the last
slide
i i do want to say that active inference
has this
wonderful uh part of it that i'm very
attracted to
and that is that it it provides
a way for an organism acting in its
environment
to play it by ear to to
to learn as it goes to be to have a
process
of learning a goal for
learning an action that can evolve over
time
right so so so if we were gonna program
an active inference robot
we would not be giving it a formula for
you know do
this 10 points do that five points now
find a way to act in the world where you
where you
you know maximize the number of points
you can get it's not really like that
and the world is
for for for in a real setting the world
is far too complex
for someone to pre-program how many
points you get for certain
activities or reaching certain goals
right so
a intelligent agent has to be able to
alter its its understanding of the world
and its goals at the same time to and
we'll talk about this again but to
balance
exploitation of what it knows already to
use what it knows about the
current situation and exploration
jumping into new uh new unknowns
uh considering new proposals concerning
new rearrangements
so so the so active inference and really
the
structural development and evolution of
all of life and ecosystems and cells and
communications
between organisms and all of that is is
kind of
built on this balance between
exploitation and exploration and you
might think of that in various ways
between old and new um you could even
think of that in terms of
like in modern day society to a degree
you could even think of it in terms of
liberal political versus conservative
political in their best sense that is a
you know conservative political might be
more
more interested in relying on tradition
and then
exploiting their current knowledge and
perhaps a liberal might be more
interested in exploring new ideas and
and taking the leaps of you know into
the into the unknown to
to learn something new and do and do
something better to improve a process to
change a process right so decision
making is very much a balance between
those two
uh exploitation exploration and active
inference provides a mechanism
by which that can occur quite naturally
and
i won't even go into detail to say that
an action model and reducing uncertainty
on that helps you act in
unknown unknowns i think it's something
unknown unknowns that's correct yeah of
which there are
plenty all right now slide five
uh i guess this is following up on
active inference just a bit
um and i think we've talked on most of
these things
uh the uh
yeah i think we have great the whole the
whole point is to resolve
expected uncertainty great so okay good
so
next six
all right so i just want to touch a a
few just a few ideas on cooperation and
communication
so uh actually cooperation and
communication are
you know go hand in hand right they may
have even evolved
together possibly so um
cooperation is the is it
really is almost the rule in the in the
in our world
life cooperates in so many ways
so many ways and the more we study it
the more we realize how deep
the cooperative cooperation is with you
know within a
species within a within between species
between trees and fungus between within
ecosystems
between ecosystems i mean it's just
cooperation is everywhere and as i said
last
in our last show if you want evidence of
it that is
if you want mind-blowing evidence and
cooperation just think of your own body
the trillion of cells that are
cooperating to for you to be what you
are right
so um cooperation exists everywhere
and it is nearly impossible without
communication
like you cannot cooperate with someone
if you don't co-op communicate
and the richer the communication the at
least potentially the richer the
cooperation
um and obviously by cooperation i mean
black communication i mean honest
communication
dishonest communication is hardly
communication right so we're talking
about honest
exchanges between cells between people
between societies um
so it's interesting though that you know
like to take your
body for example you have all these
trillion cells
and they don't have to cooperate i mean
there's you know they cannot cooperate
and sometimes they don't cooperate with
each other
and they can act independently to some
degree
right so there's always throughout the
universe there's this tension
between what cooperation provides
and what the individual
you know what the individual might want
to how it might want to behave
if it were just left to its own to its
own right
so why would anything cooperate
and and the the kind of the big picture
answered that question is because it
reduces expected uncertainty it's
again the it reduces free energy
so by cooperation a
an organism can assure itself of
survival it can
make its survival easier it can make
communication easier it can
you know do have all these benefits
right
so nevertheless every given moment
is this there's this tenuous balance
between you know do i continue to
cooperate
in this in this sphere or or
or not and who and who is and at what
to what extent do i cooperate do i
cooperate within my
uh family and
or in my community and in and or in my
society
and or between societies that like at
what level am i interested
in cooperating right and the
you know the answer the general answer
that question is i am interested in
cooperating on every level in which
uncertain my uncertainty is reduced my
my vitality is insured and my
uncertainty is reduced right
so it crossed the layers across scales
but we do see this
examples of when cooperation fails and
one example that i like to use is the
example of cancer in a body
the cells cells
transform cells start to not cooperate
with the uh the uh you know with their
milieu with their tissues with their
with their environment so uh
so my question for listeners
is uh so we have an idea of what
cooperation means
and then what is the opposite of
cooperation
like you might think okay well the
opposite of cooperation is selfishness
and i would i would suggest you know
maybe
in certain circumstances that seems
pretty clear but
in a more general sense maybe that's not
the opposite of cooperation
right maybe maybe there's
almost always cooperation and what
changes
is the extent of self of the
agent or you know the organism that's
that that is
taking the action for example
cancer cells cooperate with you know
they cooperate with each other at least
so um and they and they might cooperate
within their
you know within their very small tumor
milieu
there's a lot of communication that
happens between cancer cells once a
cancer forms a tremendous
communication that goes on between
cancer cells
so maybe it's not maybe it's not so
useful for us to think of cooperation
versus selfishness but rather
cooperation as a as a scale
scales of cooperation in the extent like
am i cooperating with my immediate
family with my
you know like or or or am i cooperating
with
societies that are far-flung and halfway
across the world right
to to the degree that we understand
ourself
to be extended we are cooperating with
i mean you have to understand that right
if i understand that i am part of this
environment this ecology then my
any actions i take to benefit the
ecology are actions that i take to
benefit myself
right so if my sense of self is extended
out
to the world to the or to the degree
that it's extended out to the world
i am interested in cooperating
with myself to better myself to reduce
my overall
uncertainty right so cancer perhaps is
it's not really a matter of being
selfish perhaps like i can't you know
people say
cancers are really selfish they're just
gonna they're just gonna
you know only pay attention to what's
good for them
yeah but that but they're cooperating
they're cooperating with a smaller group
and because they're cooperating with a
smaller group and that because their
extensive self is reduced
their capacity for cognition is reduced
and
you know we're talking we're just kind
of anthropomorphic here but
you know they they they would have a
small tumor would have a
more difficult time understanding the
long-term effects
their long-term effects because their
their cognitive
data is to a small
set of cells versus the human body which
has
the full cooperation of the brain and
the feet and the
hands and the understanding and the
capacity to
use your mouth to ask others what's
going to happen next right so
the more you the more you're the more
you extend into the world and are
cooperating with the world the larger
your
cognitive capacity the larger your
problem solving capacity
and the better you will be at
understanding
in the long term you know the outcomes
of your actions and
how that's going to affect your own um
you know how it's going to affect you as
an individual and you as an extended
self
okay so i got a little off there but uh
you know what i'm just saying
cooperation is everywhere and it's all
about
communication and shared computational
capacity and shared decision making
the potential for more more
[Music]
cognitive capacity and better decision
making great
the only point i'd make here as a ant
researcher and
have thought about conflict and
cooperation across scales
is that it's really a story we're
telling about a certain outcome
like when the white blood cell eats a
cancer cell is that altruism at the
higher level is it a conflict at the
lower level
so it's a scale-dependent and it's often
a perspectival
narrative that we're telling about what
cooperation is
and um it's just like yin and yang
there's a compliment between what we
call cooperation and communication
they're like the good guy and the bad
guy they come into existence
when we have fitness and free energy to
dissipate
so we need a story that allows us to act
in that gray zone instead of
getting fatalistic about competition or
getting utopian about cooperation
because this
is not going to be necessarily a smooth
and lovey-dovey ride
with cooperation nowhere is it in the
body so it's like a very
nice nuanced way and that's why we fall
back to active inference
rather than an ism or a specific
metaphor
of choice like the selfish gene right
right
excellent yeah and just to just to
underline that
this project is not about asking people
to behave
like super altruistically or something
like that or to cooperate you know
beyond what would be natural that that
would never
work it would fail it would fail because
that's not
what that's not how it work that's not
how what life is doing that's not how
life is working
so you know we just really just need to
be
set up our system set up our processes
set up our societal decision making you
know
ways we go about making decisions and
just
align ourselves with what we actually
are and what life is actually doing and
that means
that there is a continual conflict
between cooperation
and uh you know and not cooperation
between an and kind of an individualism
and a more cooperative stance that's
just like there's a ongoing conflict
between
exploitation and exploration between
you know conservative and liberal
between old information
the value of old information and the
value of new information this is a
all of this is a is a dance it's a
dynamic
dance right so but there is a sweet spot
in that dance there is a a place to
hover a sphere to hover in where
uh you're balancing all and new
exploitation
exploration uh conservative liberal
you're balancing them and because you're
on that in that sweet spot in that
critical
area you're able to
do about the best that any organism
could do under uncertainty
and life the magnificence of life
is the proof of that
awesome two seven okay
speaking of life yeah right
so so uh in our last talk i had
mentioned that
um that complexity
is uh you can you can think of it at
least in a certain way you can think of
it as problem solving capacity
organisms complexify and environments
complexify ecologies complexify in order
to solve
ever more difficult challenging problems
right
so it is not true that that complexity
is just a path to
to chaos and
failure right systems do fail i mean
obviously that does happen there's
there's complex systems that can fail
but by and large
complexity is a path to in greater
problem-solving capacity so
humans are complex so you know of all
the organisms on the planet we're pretty
complex we have
complex brains we we have complex
cognitive processes we can we think
about what might happen
in a thousand years and we're concerned
about what might happen in a thousand
years that's you know that's seen
that's enormously complex say com
compared to
a bacteria that doesn't have a central
nervous system
so because we're complex and this is
this is true for all organisms in
general that the more complex an
organism is the more complex it's needs
all right it's it's the more the more
feelers it has out
in the universe the more more extended
it is into the universe in a sense
and that is certainly true for humans
and uh this this table is some needs
according to maslo
maslow and i just want to mention these
as an example
not not that these are the needs we
should focus on but just as an example
of
of needs he i think he has maybe nine or
eight or nine of their i think
but affection we we just we want to be
loved and we want to love both you know
we want to share friendships it makes us
happy to do that we
we want to be creative we want to create
things we want to
build skills we want to have freedom to
associate
who with whom we want to associate and
freedom to move about and look around
and poke around and
look under things we you know we want to
participate we want to cooperate we
we want to understand we want to learn
learning is fun
for you know hopefully learning it's fun
we
we want the rest when we're tired we
want to
get some exercise we want to move about
you know
we need to relax sometimes like all
these things
this is these are if we can call these
core human needs
these speak to something that i've i
think briefly mentioned
the last uh talk which which is called
essential variables
so if an organism is if it's purpose
intrinsic purpose is to maintain
vitality into the future
well you know what what are those
variables
that are important in maintaining
vitality you know like you can think you
could think of a few
important things right off the top of
that like fresh water to drink
you know clean air to breathe the food
shelter you know like you could start to
think of what some of these essential
variables might be but i would like to
suggest that some of these core human
needs
somehow fit into the concept of
essential variables
humans need to be humans need affection
you we will be sick if we don't have
affection
right we will be sick if we don't have
freedom we will be ill
and we won't be able to and and and we
won't be able to solve
we won't be able to be good problem
solvers in our environment if we're
if we're hampered by a lack of meeting
essential variables
you know will be will be worse
so the point of all that is when we
think about
a complex organism like a human we can
think about complex needs
and then we can think about okay so now
it's starting to become clear when we're
reducing uncertainty
we're reducing uncertainty about these
essential variables which might
touch on things like the the eight or so
nine uh core needs that i'm listing
so i wanted for example i want to have
i don't want to be uncertain that i will
be loved in the future you know or that
i'll have food to eat or that i'll be
able to move about freely i would like
to be fairly certain that
that is i'm going to have those freedoms
i'm going to have these needs met
right and so again then we're not
talking about some
big computational calculator thing that
for this project is this
is this is about heart and soul and
being a human
even more human than society allows us
to be
today like you know society is not set
up
our society is not set up to
to focus on providing
for these complex human needs right i
mean we have poverty we have
billions of people in poverty in the
world and the
you that's already like all kinds of
needs are not met
because someone doesn't have the you
know the
financial capacity to
to do what they need to do right so
uh so uh we can
we can there's one last thing on this
slide this little phrase that i like to
use
is the solving problems that matter
right so
so society might solve all kinds of
problems for example if i work for a
manufacturer that is producing some like
you know let's say a
some commercial relatively
useless product that people are
uh that they're that people are buying
because the
commercialism is is pushed
you know i made maybe i'm solving the
immediate problem of making an income so
that i can pay my rent but beyond that
am i solving problems that matter you
know i don't have a good example maybe
someone else does the useless thing that
many people do in their with their
life's
work you know their 40 hours a week is
doing something
useless there was a book there was a
book there was a book about that a while
ago and they had a phrase but
i forget exactly what his phrase was
well i don't know if it was a
family-friendly phrase but i think i
know it but yeah i don't think it was
yeah
i hesitate to say it because it wasn't
family friends friendly
you know it's like you know uh whose
team our team like that kind of a call
and response like which problems
the ones that matter i mean then what
does it mean to matter well that's our
preferences and our affordances
and then as far as cases where the work
or the problem doesn't matter
there's times where the person might
think that the problem matters
but when you pull back it's actually a
non-linear response
where even if it does matter the issue
that they're concerned about
that their effort may not be the most
efficacious
and this isn't going to go back to
another optimization you must be engaged
in the most efficacious
um because we're actually putting space
for play and identity
and participation understanding all
these attributes that aren't just
some simple cybernetic like action
selection
but it's really important to keep this
as our guiding light it's the problems
and
those are the salient ones the ones that
matter but we need to be informed by our
values
yeah yeah and obviously we're talking
high level here we're
we're trying to give a context for this
whole thing of what could society be
and how would we go about measuring
fitness and
you know what is a society supposed to
accomplish and for whom
and then we have to talk about the you
know these these high level
concepts because they can be guides for
us right so the just the phrase solving
problems that matter it can be a useful
guide because
it remember it reminds us oh yeah what
what matters and what am i doing with my
life and what are we doing in society
with our lives
are we doing things are we solving
problems that matter
and you know obviously there's a whole
bunch of enormous problems that we're
not solving right
like climate change and other things you
know
if society was solving problems that
matter that would be like
enormous armies of biologists and
you know other people the uh ecologists
and
and field workers and all kinds of
people
you know focusing on the problems that
matter most
for for happiness and survival and
currently in today's world
you know that that is heating up heating
up to be
climate change and biodiversity loss and
you know
ecological destruction and pollution and
groundwater depletion and like all the
things that that
were were pushed you know
all the damage we've done to our to our
world
certainly cleaning those problems up
ought to be
among the problems that matter okay
so uh there we go i think uh
uh one last thing on this slide photo or
in the bottom right
i i bring the topic of culture in
and i just want to just say a word about
culture from an
active enforcement a viewpoint so
you know at its best culture
is a remembering of what is important
to teach you know to to not only to
teach new people to
each new you know new young adults as
they
mature what's important but also to
to offload some of the computational
burden that individuals would otherwise
face so
if i have to figure out everything for
myself from you know from scratch as an
organism
oh that's tough it is so much easier for
my for me
if my peers you know point me in the
right direction
tell me you know give me some indication
of what's dangerous what's not dangerous
what's important what's not important
give me some guidance i can learn so
much faster if i have some good guidance
and uh and also if i can just rely on
culture to
just to you know like okay you know my
culture
does this thing and i'm not gonna maybe
even think about it too deeply because
i'm you know like if my culture is good
it's maybe reflecting in some
capacity this importance of putting
attention on those things that matter
right so now we've now talked about two
important things here actually
uh culture and how culture relates to uh
to the reduction of uncertainty overall
and then uh also attention and the role
of culture
in directing attention so those are
themes that we'll
be coming back on nice so
attention attention and essential
variables you know like
those go together right if we've not
obtained attention to essential
variables
then our whole free energy minimization
thing is
not functioning correctly right because
we have to put attention on those things
that are important
okay all right next all right so now we
get to the slide where i get to ask you
and
any any listeners like what does this
mean practically so we've talked about
all these high level concepts we've
given
some context for you know for who we are
and what we might need and
what a what a societal system is
supposed to do
and those were all fairly high level
disc
discussions and now it may be it's time
just to talk a little bit about what
that might actually mean
in a practical sense so
the title of the slide is practical
indications but up down at the bottom i
have
also known as how do you solve problems
because the two are the same thing like
this is the question
how do you how do we solve how do we how
do we
um how do we how do we solve problems
how do we focus on
uh if we're good at problem solving if
we're good at solving problems how do we
do it
and uh obviously we want if we're going
to build new societal systems we want to
build societal systems that help us
that facilitate our problem-solving
capacity facilitate our capacity to
reduce
uncertainty expected uncertainty right
so i'm just going to list
some things and maybe on the first you
know in the first read of this
just you can we can just acknowledge
like okay yeah that's how we solve
problems we
number one there we get we gather data
we we
we sense our world you know obviously
right
that's how an organism solves a problem
and even knows that there's a problem to
solve for that matter
and we remember we remember what we did
maybe last week or last year we remember
how we solved something before we
remember that this situation is
dangerous
and we might want to avoid it in the
future so we remember remember
we anticipate or make forecasts and obvi
and
we've already talked about the
importance of anticipation forever for
cognition in any organism
and and cooperate we cooperate with
those around us we
we have a problem to solve and we get
some help maybe
we solve it together we we work together
we build a house together we
we you know build a jumbo chat together
we do all these things together we
farm together but what's
uh so cooperation is one way to solve a
problem and then
what does cooperation entail well it
requires that we
maybe we as a group we reward
uh pro-social or cooperative behavior
and maybe penalize
anti-social behavior you know i mean
that's
in game theory they've done all these
studies about cooperation and it's
pretty
you know there's some really good ideas
pretty clear ideas basic ideas of
when do when how do you actually
facilitate cooperation
and and what makes cooperation go down
the toilet
right so uh if your communication
really helps cooperation rewarding uh
pro-social behavior
transparency helps cooperation fairness
helps coop
like all these we know all these things
right from from common experiences in
life
and also from studies in game theory in
other fields
so uh so solve a problem we cooperate we
communicate we
we direct attention there's that word
attention again we direct our attention
to those things that matter
we learn from our actions and
observations so we update our models of
things
when we realize like oh no i guess the
world doesn't work that way
i should i should learn something but
the world is a little more
it works differently than i was
anticipating or i
thought before uh and then we act to
reduce expected uncertainty we
experiment we
we we have goal directed activities
our actions where we you know try to
that's the exploitation aspect and then
we also have the exploration aspect
action for epistemic and again then we
have this exploration versus
exploitation trade-off so so i'm not i'm
just saying what i think everyone
already understands i'm just making a
list here but now the question is okay
fine so that's how we solve problems
how do each of these play out
in a societal system setting
so i you know if i think if we wanted to
we won't because we don't have time but
i think if we wanted to
we could list like 500 ways this this
any of these play out and it's maybe
should play out or could play out
in a in a healthy society is a society
that's good at solving problems
uh i had already mentioned one earlier
so like let's just say on the topic of
of anticipation wouldn't it be
reasonable
to somehow uh remember
who remember and pay attention to who is
good at
who is good at anticipating the future
so if
you know if a certain political figure
or uh you know a certain organization is
that
turns out to have a really good track
record of accurately predicting what's
going to happen next well then maybe we
want to pay attention to them
and pay more attention to them to uh
than to others who have a terrible track
record of
of uh predicting what's going to happen
next you know like if a politician says
oh if you
do this if you do a then b is going to
happen well if
you know if by and large those kinds of
predictions are wrong
then you know politicians probably not
worth much
but but not just in politics obviously
we may
we anticipate and like for example
that's what science does
science is you know awash with
trying to figure out how the world works
and what's going to happen next
and so so that's another area that we
could
you know a healthy society might really
support the scientific
uh you know the scientific endeavor
and pay attention to what scientists are
saying like for example with climate
change and
other things you know if the whole
scientific world is saying hey this is
serious you've got to pay you've got
gotta do something about it
well then maybe a healthy society would
actually do something about it right
um honesty the honesty i'm just picking
out things off the list you know but i
think we could talk for
numerous hours about how any of these
might play out in a
in a real setting right um honesty so
uh look at look at the dis look at the
look
the amount of dishonest uh information
or manipulated information that is
flowing around us today in this world
um you know why is why is that i mean
obviously a healthy society would want
to
share uh honest and valid information
let's call it quality information you
know models are good models are built on
quality information
so you know
why here's a question why in our world
why is there so much just information
and i would i would suggest that at
least some of it
is due to the fact that
individuals and organizations
corporations
are fantastically rewarded
for putting out dishonest
information right i mean i mean just
think of a thief i can
i can call you up in a phone scam and if
i
can convince you that i'm your bank
and i need your account number then i
can have
enormous rewards for being you know
dastardly dishonest
you but but it's true i mean maybe
that's an extreme example but it's true
in just
ordinary examples of business and life
that
one can be rewarded greatly
or being fairly dishonest or you know
putting out
something less than quality information
and then you gotta
then you gotta ask okay well then if if
you know like we don't society doesn't
want to reward
anti-social anti uh you know
and anti-transparent anti-honest
uh behavior how how how would a society
reward pro-social honest behavior
transpl how would it maybe a society
could become more transparent so
transparency obviously to be a part of
this
but but um i'm i'm sort of honing in
i don't know if you if you can tell but
i'm sort of honing in just on this
little
question about how do we what how do we
reward
behaviors in this world as a society and
then that suddenly
brings up the question of the how does
an economic system work and
how does what what how do we
view money and how do we view income and
how do we
use money and income in our lives
and is there some way that we could
reinvent
an economy and reinvent money so
that it wasn't rewarding uh you know
reinvent rules and reinvent whatever we
need to reinvent so that we are actually
day-to-day moment to moment we're
rewarding cooperative
pro-social behavior and and honest
behavior so like how do we do that
now i have some ideas on how to do that
but
that's in the part three of the paper so
we'll get to them later
so i don't want to go much further on
this but i'm just suggesting that
that that we could spend you know each
of these could raise
a hundred ideas of how to what we could
do
in a healthier society to improve our
capacity for group problem solving
nice points good for nine
yeah i always think i am but but hold on
one second
on the right hand side of slide eight
are a few other ideas so
um uh you know obviously
we've already talked about fit the
societal systems measuring the fitness
of them
so um you know how do we how do
that's also a general answer to this
question of how do we build a society
that is more fit
well we actually measure things that are
important and we score them
and we share that information widely so
we know how we're doing
so we know so we can evaluate either our
systems or our organizations or our
institutions or
society at large or those kinds of
things so
metrics are important
i already mentioned science and critical
thinking are important so that touches
on the educational system for example
the healthy educational system would
really value
critical thinking and would train
individuals to be
critical thinkers at an early age i
would think
and then obviously then removing the
barriers to cooperation
this society has enormous barriers to
cooperation
i might want to get it for here's just
one example out of what could be a
million examples
say that i was kind of uh wanted to make
the world i wanted to
use my life's energy my work time my 40
hours a week
of work a week to make the world a
better place
so i want to jump in and i want to uh
i don't know let's say i want to teach
teach kids little
children you know maybe i want to be a
teacher be a good teacher
well that's great fantastic but
if i do that i have to pay a financial
penalty like
i'm not going to i could become a banker
instead of suppose those are my two
choices i could become a banker or a
finance minute finance person or
something
or i could become a teacher well i'm
going to society is going to reward me
greatly for being a
banker or a finance person and it's
going to
not reward me very well for being a
teacher
so i might want to cooperate i might
want to
work to for the betterment of humankind
but
if i do there's a good chance i'm going
to be relatively poor
you know like i pay a heavy price for
that and that's a that's just a barrier
to cooperation
cooperate we should design systems so
that the
cooperation becomes the default easy no
that like the
do it this way because it's good for
everyone it's good for you and
uh sure you want to teach well great we
have come on in here's
here's opportunities for you to teach
and you're not going to pay a penalty
for becoming a teacher you know you're
this is going to be easy you can be
if you want to be a teacher and help
young children learn better
great here's wonderful opportunities and
you're not going to have to
pay a penalty for doing that we're going
to
actually just the opposite we're going
to reward you for doing it
okay now we're done with uh slide nine
or slide it sounds good to nine
okay so um so i
the only thing i really want to say
about this this slide is that this
the concept of the societal systems as a
cognitive architecture
i you know i you know probably somewhere
in the literature there's something
you know talking about that in some
sense but i it's
i think maybe i don't know if it's as
kind of like
pointed as i'm making it in this series
and there
and there really is no name for what is
what is the name
for the set of societal systems
that helps the society that facilitates
societal cognition what is the name of
that
and there isn't a name you know it's
it's not an economic system and it's not
a governance system because that's just
those are just some
systems that are that have their own
connotations so what is the name of this
whole set of integrated systems that
helps as society to think well there is
no name so i
i mean i there is no formal name and so
you can't look at if you're going to
search in the literature on this topic
there's no
there's no term to search for and uh so
i thought maybe it would be useful if i
try to suggest some terms at least
and i and i suggest the term uh societal
cognitive architecture for the general
the general idea that societal systems
are a cognitive architecture for society
but then for the more specific
developing de novo systems to be good
at facilitating societal cognition i
suggest the term sales uh societal
societal active inference and learning
systems um
i mean maybe there's some other better
trim i don't know but i i
threw together this one so it's sales
that i'm interested in developing new
new
designs of societal systems that excel
facilitate uh sell facilitating societal
cognition
so uh you know if one of these terms
catch on maybe then in the future we'll
be able to if we're interested in the
topic we can actually do a search on
google and
we'll find a you know 100 papers or a
thousand papers on
some of these topics well just one quick
on that it points to the need for
improved cognitive architecture
such as knowledge management tools that
help us collaborate and find
information semantically like
information is for our experience
because you're right it is fragmented
and therefore
unproductive across truly different
disciplines and different jargons
different languages as well unscanned
documents
things that are just only on someone's
uh notepad just
it's all over the place right and
and and sometimes a thing doesn't really
exist until you name it and then it and
then it sort of exists for the larger
it can't exist for the larger society so
i'm name i'm naming this
because maybe if we name it we can talk
about it you know
yes the other the other problem there is
like when i go to expl it would be much
easier for me
to just throw out a term like cognitive
social cognitive
societal architecture and if people
understood that term then i wouldn't
have to spend a half hour
trying to explain what it is that i'm
talking about right so
terms terms can help if we have a shared
understanding of what their meaning is
what what is not sales because it's a
you know what is what's not part of the
function of the body
how do we differentiate what is apart
from that instead of this just being
the one-to-one rapper around economics
governance legal et cetera et cetera
right right right good point and uh i
don't i really might
my use of the term sales i'm suggesting
it for use
really in this de novo design you know
process
of of creating new systems so
um quite true the the the the
you know the cognitive the concepts of
cognition that we've been talking about
they are universal so uh
it is true but we're kind of kind of
focusing on just
sales as a term for the kind of r
d project r d projects to move forward
that might
uh look at the de novo designs of new
systems
right just the pond traveling sales
person
it's a problem you know it's a hard
problem actually
it's traveling salesperson problem
yes it is
all right so with that uh we are
uh uh ready to move on to uh
the actual talk cool today
drum rolls please drum roll schedule the
time
awesome the second is the second part
you know this is um a different
media we're kind of spilling above and
beyond what you've wrote in the papers
because the three papers are the version
of reference
that's where people will cite but
actually in this increasingly
digitized insightable world perhaps the
things that you're
sharing with us as well as even the
anonymous content that people produce on
a jam board or live chat like this all
becomes part of how we
produce our uncertainty and act yeah
yeah
and and hopefully becomes part of the
record and part of the useful record for
for moving forward on some of these
concepts
okay so part one was all about world
view it was
you know high level discussions high
level topics about
what creates a world view and how what
kind of world view would be useful in
the setting for
developing new systems and then now
we're moving on to the more nuts and
bolts of things a little bit more
in the sense of why are we even
motivated to
to transform and uh and
if we do want to develop new systems
uh what kind of strategy you know what
like
[Music]
it's it's not enough just to come up
with some great design
it has to be viable in the sense that it
can be implemented there has to be some
way to actually
use these ideas actually live these
ideas
um and if there's not then we're sort of
wasting our time
so strategy is core to the whole
proposed r d program
right um so
yeah so i'm going to in in part two i
talk about really
uh i try to argue a given narrative in
part two that i try to argue that
transformation is prudent
given the risks we face attractive given
its potential benefits
and achievable given the current
political financial
and social constraints so that's what i
hope to accomplish in this paper
and that's what i hope to accomplish in
this this talk too
cool all right so on the question of
motivation like why transform
we we touched on some of these ideas in
our first talk
but i i would just like to point out
that we face
a host of extremely difficult problems
climate change being one of them
climate change biodiversity laws
groundwater depletion
soils depletion
poverty financial
uh uncertainty uh
you know in that sense debt might play
into that role
um you know if you make a list of all
the
very serious problems that humanity
faces it's kind of a long list
migration and then one problem causes
another so
climate change is certainly likely
almost certainly will increase the
number of refugees trying to cross
borders people living without homes that
are fleeing
areas that are not that don't have
enough water or are not livable
or you know things like that so one
problem causes the other
and you know what what what everyone is
fearful of happening is is that
you have this the collection of 10 or 20
really serious problems and then
something happens to flare one of them
up
and then suddenly that problem you know
transfers to other problems and then
you have uh just one you know like
everything's connected so
if one part of our global society gives
sway
it could be that everything starts to
kind of fall apart
so there is a fear of that and there is
a need to address these
problems independently and then also
in a holistic sense and i would like to
emphasize that these problems we face
are in a sense symptoms not really
problems in and of themselves they're
symptoms
of a failure of society
up you know to today a failure to
address the needs
of of the society a failure to reduce
uncertainty and failure to do exactly
what we were talking about
in the previous part of this talk right
so so
climate change climate change is because
we failed to take action we've known
about climate change for
60 years i don't know i mean like it's
it's been in the it's been
it's been um uh in the scientific world
like in a
in a major way uh with major agreement
on the
implications and the basic processes and
the
and what it means to society that's been
talked about
that there was you know
the scientific world was on this 30
years ago
and talking about it and writing papers
and having you know so
so we didn't society didn't listen
and it didn't and i would say it didn't
listen for a reason because
if it had listened to those warnings it
society would have had to have changed
and there are elements of society
that are doing well
and are maybe not so interested in
changing behaviors and
especially changing power distributions
right so uh the people that the
power the powers that more or less guide
society
we're not interested in dealing with
our serious problems because we have
they have gotten worse
over the last 50 years or whatever
these problems have amplified if you
don't solve a problem it tends to fester
and get larger that's exactly what's
happened now we're at
the period of not only
not only will climate change you know is
climate change going to
affect the gdp that's that's that's
uh yes it's the real problem is
are we going to go extinct i mean this
is serious
this is you know like this is life and
death now for
if not if not millions or billions of
people it's life and death for our
species
we have to deal with this in some kind
of bold
way or we we won't have children on this
planet
and you know whatever in uh 50 years 100
years 200 years
humans won't be a thing so that's how
i say that because uh that's how badly
society has failed us we are at the
brink of falling off a cliff
we maybe we're already maybe we already
fell off a cliff and we just
don't quite realize it yet
like what what kind of healthy organism
puts itself in commits suicide like what
healthy system commits suicide
none really only the phoenix
yeah only the phoenix yeah and you know
that maybe it worked out for that one
okay it
sort of it rose i guess but uh and maybe
we'll do the same but
uh you know my point is is that
the serious problems we face are all
symptoms of our lack of cognitive
capacity at the societal level
and there were there have been there are
there have been solutions to all these
problems
for decades and we simply have
not taken them because because doing so
would have disrupted
i think the distribution of power in
society and
that just people weren't willing to do
that
okay so um so in this paper
on this call for transformational change
so i am i'm trying
to i'm calling for transformational
change right now but
i'm not alone so this this idea of we
need bold change this is not just me
in a vacuum this is uh most of the
scientific world really
and uh most of the global policy making
world
and a large section of the global public
is all realizing that we are in deep
trouble and we need to change
not incrementally not slowly but rapidly
and deeply and across every aspect of
society so i'll just use the words
this is a from the 2019 global
assessment
from the ipbes
the un uh they as they in their words
uh current and national they say current
national global programs are
insufficient to avoid you know
catastrophe
and they call for a transformational
change they use the word
transformational
and they define it as a fundamental
system-wide reorganization
across technical technological economic
social factors
including paradigms goals and values i
mean
essentially uh
you know enormous fundamental change in
how we
understand ourselves how we understand
the world how we behave what we do for a
living
how industry works how consumerism works
what products we make how we recycle
like
how much energy we use how where we get
our energy
so so um i think maybe i don't know i
don't want to put words in the
human's mouth but i think maybe they
were really still kind of talking about
um you know like improving
current systems you know like we can
improve our economic system
to do this we can improve our we can
take bold steps within our governance
systems we can take bold steps
within our economic systems financial
systems we can do better there's ways
that we can do better
i would like to very much agree with
that there are ways we can do better we
should
we should i would i would put that under
the category of reform
we should do everything in our power to
reform the existing systems
because that is the quickest bang for
the buck i mean we can do more
isn't it imperative that we act
and put our energies behind reforming
as best we can the existing systems
working within existing systems
and reforming them so they can do a
better job is so that
we can reach some kind of transformation
even within existing systems
but but this uh this proposed r d
program and my interests
are are beyond that so i'm not i i'm not
you know my interest here is
uh not in reform not in improving
capitalism for example or or
representative democracy it is in
building de novo systems from the ground
up that
are fit for purpose as as we've been
talking about
so you know i that's what i mean when i
say
societal transformation i mean i mean
shifting to
building testing and shifting to new
systems
and in the you know we're familiar with
these kind of concepts
when we download software and in the
software world
there the terms are usually updates so
like
you know i'm going to update my software
minor improvement i'm going to upgrade
my software to a new version i'm going
to get you know version four instead of
version three so that's kind of like
big reform i'm gonna get an upgrade
then migration so i'm gonna do i don't
even like this
this company or this product i'm gonna
switch to open source
and i'm gonna use the linux operating
system or some other
i'm going to do something else i'm going
to use some entirely new system because
the old one really doesn't work very
well
so so my focus is on this the you know
is a migration
the the testing development uh uh
and uh implementation of de novo
designed
societal systems um
okay so i think uh you know and and a
science driven
this in a science-driven process so
that's important to add to
okay so lots of people calling for
transformational change and that's what
this
paper is about transformation understood
as migration
to new systems um
on slide 12 uh
i think maybe i mean others might
disagree but i think maybe this is the
first series in the literature that
uh in the science literature that really
lays out a r d program that aims to
tackle this de novo design of new
systems
um i don't i've not seen any others that
are that are
kind of comparable so i think we're
maybe
you know paving new ground here perhaps
at least i hope
uh i want to emphasize something we
talked about on the in the last talk
that this is uh
we're talking about second order
sciences as opposed to
first order science so first order
science again is
what we normally think of as science as
someone is doing experiments they're
they're
detached from the experiment the
scientists are detached they're just
they set it up they let the experiment
run they they don't interfere
they they just record what happened and
hopefully they gain some knowledge from
doing so
fantastic stuff most of science is all
this is first order science is one
is wonderful but for these kinds of
problems for this kind of
problem that we're facing this global
climate
global crisis problem this i think
uh requires what is called
second order science and there's a in my
series i
i cite the work by phase you know on
this topic and that's a this great
article i
i recommend that to everyone that it's
in the paper so you can get it there but
he describes what
they i should say today it's a long list
of authors describe what they mean by
a second-order science and why it's
important
and uh they just kind of in a nutshell
we're talking about in our case building
new systems we're talking about
kind of a metal learning so we're
learning to learn we're
we're learning to build new systems that
help us to learn and build new systems
right we want to excel
at learning that's the whole concept of
this we we want a society that excels at
learning and problem solving
and adaptation and we're and we're in
the process of learning
to build new systems that produce this
effect so it's kind of a meta learning
science uh meta learning process and
and just in general the second order
science is
the focus is on process the effort is
value driven
and the part and the scientists are
participants along with stakeholders who
together
learn develop and evaluate solutions
together so
it's quite different from first order
science and it's exactly the kind of
science i think that is necessary for
this larger
meta learning project
in the in the paper i i i i talk about
six overarching systems i just want to
say that that's what we're focused on
here
so economic uh their economic governance
legal health
analytical and educational systems those
are the ones i've chosen to focus on
and each of them can be split down
further like in in my terminology the
economic system also includes a monetary
system and a financial system
and so on and each of these can be split
down
further so that's what we're doing we're
like trying to
develop designs for each of these that
are integrated not not
just hey let's just build a new economic
system and leave everything else and
change we'll do the economic system
first
that's not the that's not the point of
the process the idea is
how can we build a integrated set
of systems of full cognitive
architecture that helps us to
achieve these goals and it's really a
nice dovetailing with development
is what organisms do that's embryonic
development or colony level development
or the niche being modified so it's like
research and development
research information foraging um
whatever we want to think about
information foraging to mean here with
research or just search but
it's like we already have design latency
within
potentially even the structures we have
so how are we going to pull out of the
tailspin
if that's what we're in to build towards
developing a healthier trajectory
that's right we're in the process of
evolution you know
[Music]
and and every organism is evolving
exactly as you say
and and developing so we're just being a
part of that
uh and in a you know
quite a quite a sensible part of that i
might add too it's kind of like
oh we're faced with severe problems that
we might uh
have a masked eye off of humans or go
extinct but because of so
let me think what would be a good idea
oh let's do
let's think about doing things
differently let's try to build a
different way to
live our lives you know that's just kind
of like duh
that's a good idea let's let's find a
better way to live our lives and be more
cooperative and have a healthier world
that's an excellent idea um
okay so uh in this is kind of a warm-up
to what's coming
in the paper i i speak a lot about local
community
and i just want to emphasize or i want
to explain what that means a little bit
so um uh for one thing i i call
society a organism or a superorganism
and a cognitive organism with that and
uh and by society i mean really a
society of any size so in particular
i'm interested in local communities for
some reasons it'll become clear shortly
so a local community might be just like
a fraction of a city not even a full
city and not even a political body not a
like a formal political body but a
group of people who in particular have
in this case are particularly interested
in uh
participating in trying out and field
testing
and using some of these new systems that
we're talking about developing
so uh you know let's say uh
when i say a local community let's say
a group of a thousand people or more
could be
could be larger but not not necessarily
even a city and certainly not a nation
okay so um so i said that the u.n and
others are this is slide
13. i've said that you the u.n and
others are
come out with strong language uh calling
for a
transformational change which i think
again
you know for many uh folks involved
there i think maybe their idea
really is more what i would call reform
again very very important but it might
help here to talk about why
why reform might not be enough like why
why you know if the fee win and other
agencies and
other groups are really are really
putting up some great proposals for
reform and improvement of existing
systems
you know why am i interested in in
developing new systems why don't we just
do reform you know
if that'll do the trick let's why why
bother with more
and there's numerous reasons that i lay
out in the in the
paper number two of why i think
transformation
new system development is is necessary
and uh uh you know to start with
and as we've kind of been saying here i
you can look look at the world and the
problems that we face with climate
change and biodiversity loss and others
and you can suspect that current systems
are
incapable maybe incapable of preventing
widespread
catastrophe and securing our continued
vitality
i mean really the you know the the
report card doesn't look good
for existing systems they've done a
rather crappy job of protecting the
human health in the environment to the
to the extent that we now face
perhaps in our lifetime or soon after
perhaps a
mass die off of humans or even
extinction of humans
so you know why why would we think that
they're capable now
suddenly of of of acting differently
you know excellent to do reform i don't
want to talk anyone out of the reform
efforts because they're absolutely
important but i am suggesting that maybe
we should have a plan b
in case plan a doesn't work out so well
so uh uh you know transformation this is
a
this is a plan b in a sense and in the
end
might turn out to be better than plan a
even if reform is useful
and and helpful plan b might turn out to
be the better bet
so you can kind of catch it on both ends
there
so i just talked about a few things i
mentioned in the paper of why
you know like why why why
evidence of current systems being
incapable of preventing
a widespread catastrophe so one is the
paris agreement
and then this is quoting from one of the
un studies i believe
uh it says ambitions are broadly
consistent with cost-effective pathways
that result in a global warming of about
three degrees by 2100
with warming continuing afterwards okay
so
so you know in a practical sense you
know if the
paris agreement were interactive that's
sort of what
uh where it would lead to it is clearly
it is
you know is maybe an important agreement
but uh not enough not nearly enough it
looks like
and uh if indeed we were to reach about
three degrees centigrade change
from um historical levels uh
that is that's already in the iffy
category
of like you know how do humans what do
we do we even have a civilization if we
reach their degrees you know it's an
iffy question maybe we do maybe we find
a way to deal with it
and get by or maybe we don't maybe
that's already way too much
um and uh also the reform efforts uh
don't adequately address certain
structural uh problems
that we that we face like most reform
efforts
are not really looking at the extreme
income and income and wealth divisions
in the world
uh you know the most of the most of the
reform efforts are not
looking at how we can not have
billionaires but rather
have everyone more or less equally
engaged in
the you know economic sphere and in a
sense having
economic power to make decisions in this
world
so so even if reform efforts are useful
and good
i hope they are uh maybe they won't be
enough and maybe they won't even
touch deeply on some topics that really
need to be
addressed um so i argue
you know this this section covers
several pages but in the end i argue
that even if
even if reform efforts are are useful
and helpful uh and they're successful
and you know for what they're
shooting for they're still likely to
leave societies hampered in their
in their capacity to learn and adapt
with many unsolved problems to address
like even for example even right now
even at one
what we're at i'm not sure what degree
we're at right now
over historical levels but still below
two degrees
maybe we're 1.3 i don't know what it is
already there's nations that are you
know they're the island nations that are
not able to handle this you know like
people are already started i have to
relocate
and every indication is that that's just
going to become worse and worse
so uh even if we even if we keep the
keep it below 1.5 degrees or we keep it
below 2 degrees the warming
we're going to have severe problems
social problems
economic problems environmental problems
ecological problems and somehow we're
going to have to deal with this
harsher world than even harsher than
today
you know more dangerous than today and
more strained than today more stressful
than today and i'm suggesting that the
best way to deal with a future world
that is stressful and uncertain highly
uncertain and difficult
is to become really good at problem
solving
isn't i mean that's how you would go
about it that's you would be
if you can you would become really good
at acting
in an uncertain world and making wise
decisions so that
you don't have to suffer any more than
is necessary
um uh yeah
so that's that's you know like there
would be even even if we even if reform
is successful
it would still be useful to develop to
become
better at problem solving um and i think
that
there's great opportunity to become
better i mean as
as a whole society hasn't even really
tried to become
a good problem solver like you know in a
focused
science driven way we've never really
put our mind to this
and we can put our mind to it and i
think that would be
tremendous improvements that we could
make that's
you know that's why i wrote the series
is because i think we could do so much
better
than we're doing today which is not very
well
um let's see anything else on this slide
yes down in the lower right hand corner
i have a
kind of a long list of things that we
need to do and
i won't read it now but you know we
basically have to remake
everything from what we make how we make
it how we use it where it goes how it's
disposed of
how we treat each other how we cooperate
who we cooperate i mean just like
deep transformation from across
every aspect of human life and in human
social life
so uh you know it to me at least it's
inconceivable
that existing systems could even come
close to the
level of transformation that is actually
not only
needed but would be beneficial
like it would be really beneficial if
societies became
good at problem solving and adaptation
and it's pretty much inconceivable to
inconceivable to me at least that
existing systems and existing reform
proposals and efforts
could come close to what is actually
needed and
and would be beneficial
i think uh you know this is really
great i'm just looking for a natural
pause
point for where we would want to be what
do you think about
doing 14 going through it taking our
time
and then this r d program
being the pickup point for our third
session i know we're going slow
you're going on some great boomerangs so
it's awesome but let's walk through
leaving somebody at the end of the
second discussion what would
an r d program be that would meet the
scope and the type of these challenges
and then
three is going to be like you want to
know what it is go there
yeah and i think for for listeners
daniel and i've been talking about
you know there's a lot of material to
unpack here so i think we're going to
have
more than three videos uh but
we'll figure out what the dates will be
for them so that we can go through the
whole thing
uh you know carefully perfect um
okay so uh we'll we'll end on on slide
14 then
uh uh
maybe to start i would just like to say
that i've i'm
the the series is a proposal for you
know like a like a
soft proposal for a new r d programming
to know about development of new systems
but other people might come up with
another proposal
like you know mine maybe is just one of
many possible ways to go about
the r d program for new proposals
and i would welcome i would hope even
that it would be fantastic if there were
you know 20 projects happening around
the world
of uh aimed at this same thing and that
we and that each of these projects was
cooperating with each other so that we
can learn from each other
and and move forward you know in the
most efficient and useful most useful
way
so that's one of the reasons that i made
this
desert list is uh like what would be
if other if if if there's going to be
multiple r d programs or even if it's
just my
this just this one that i put out you
know what what would be a good
what has to be included in the r d
program you know what which which
what should be there so that we would
know that it's a you know
like a reasonably complete one and so
that we could we could compare r d
program so if i propose this one and
someone else proposes another one we can
compare say on number five
uh number five develops new integrated
systems that span all six of these major
societal systems economic governance et
cetera well
if someone else proposes one that it's
only focused on economic systems well
there's a way to just distinguish
between the two
r d programs so that's uh that's that's
part of my purpose here of laying this
out
and then it's also also the purpose that
you will see as you read the series that
i
talk about each one of these so this is
just in a sense
it's a it's a index to
the to the larger series and also one
point um
is that a scientist might say you need
to do a b and c to really study you know
the mosquitoes wing
and then of course they measure a b and
c so of course they solve the mosquitoes
wing
but actually you're laying out a
protocol for evaluating policy across
scales and then
putting up almost like a retort to
yourself at least initially
that you believe could be held against
this rubric like a report card
and then again where a policy is better
on point five or eleven or whatever it
be
we can make that decision in a way or we
can version the rubric
so this isn't just setting the target or
painting the target texas sharpshooter
paint the target after you wrote the
paper hypothesizing after the results
are known harking
this is like laying out where we do want
it to go
right exactly exactly and uh and i hope
that
uh that we refined it together as a as a
community refined this list
so that we hone it better even um
uh maybe there's some things i left out
or some things i should have said
or things i said i didn't need to say
who knows but i'm sure it could be
improved
so uh we don't have much time and i
won't go uh
i won't go into detail on these but
maybe i'll just
uh just to give a flavor i'll just talk
about a few
scattering here um so obviously
number one if you if you know you're
talking about a r d program
it might help to actually provide some
information about the scale of the
intended effect i mean
are we thinking that this r d program is
going to build uh
new systems for a uh for one particular
city
or for uh for you know for a nation or
for
you know like what scale is this whole
thing going to apply who's going to
where is it going to go if it's
successful right what is the scale and
what are the costs what are the risks
how much money is this whole thing going
to take you know and we'll talk about
that
money we'll talk about in the next next
talk
uh based on second order science which i
mentioned earlier
already uh number three it has a theory
of change like
fine you you you you tested a new system
you built it you get great computer
simulation models great
now what do we do with it how would you
ever take that
idea and make it real implement it in a
real
society somewhere how does it how does
that work
and and where is the blowback gonna be
where is the pressure is gonna be
against it what might go wrong so that
should be in there
uh theory of change um
number five it develops integrate i
claim that it's important that it
develops integrated systems across
all six of the major ones because if it
doesn't
you know if you if you build a
governance system independent from an
economic system and you're still using
the old economic system it's you're it's
not going to work very well because
they're going to be at heads with each
other
not integrated um uh
six describes the purpose of a silent
system what in the world is it supposed
to do how do we know it even worked what
you know
what do we measure fitness what what was
it supposed to accomplish and how can we
how can we evaluate it on what it did
accomplish or what it's
supposed to um uh
how does cognition played like in this
whole series as well focused on societal
cognition
maybe some other ph maybe some other r d
program doesn't even use the word
cognition maybe they have an entirely
different way to think about
what a society is and how it does and
what the purpose is so if so
you know it'd be good to say so uh
makes the work freely available to the
public uh so that
and i didn't we haven't talked about
this but i i'm the
the uh it's assumed here that whatever
is developed would be developed in an
open source way or would be freely
available to the world this is not a
proprietary
project at all
number eight it develops flexible
options that the public can choose from
well
if there is no one-size-fits-all
solution i mean that wouldn't be
very wise at all societies have to have
flexibility in how they act how they
what they implement what they choose
so hopefully it would be a the program
would develop a smorgasbord of ideas and
possibilities that could be useful in
different settings
um number 11 addresses the cultural
changes what kind of educational changes
for example would be necessary to make
this work uh there would be substantial
ones actually
because you build a new system for one
thing you would have to
explain or educate people on how the new
system is even
goes together and how it works and how
what how would you know if it's not
working you know all those kinds of
questions
um number 12 if new systems are
implemented in multiple locations
so how do is that information shared
between them how does that work
is each independent or are they
communicating or
is this all part of a larger plan to
have multiple
tests going on at the same time or are
those just independent things that come
and go as they do
uh um uh obviously number 13 develop
systems that are fair and just and then
you know you could that is reasonable uh
and uh number 14
you know what are the expected impacts
when you do simulations for this new
system
i was how does it look for energy use
and
waste generation and climate change and
biodiversity loss how
you know what are we going to get if we
um if we build these how is it going to
go what is
what is the likely outcome of these
things so that's just a few ideas that
a few topics that would be important to
address in any r d program and i've
tried my best to
address them here and even in just three
papers you know like some of these are
addressed in just a few
sentences or a few paragraphs somewhere
in the papers because
you know you would really need a book i
think or a series a series of books to
really do a
thorough job on all of these well you
know what i kind of saw almost when you
have this list is like a github or a
versioned
open source repository where people can
fork the rubrics they like they can add
more challenges they can go into detail
what do you mean by fair
what do you mean that they're just well
those are things that we actually
in active inference we can get down to
and that's not to say that we're going
to be carving out the human it means
that we're going to be
designing for ourselves and for
whoever's on board and just like the
ship makers
make it for those who are on the ship
but the ship is part of society
there's gonna be a ship with sales so i
think they'll be
such interesting conversations because
really you could
fractal into yeah seven
what is the role of information i mean i
went to a conference today on
only a fragment of that so of course
seven is going to be a big topic but
it's a
it's third order science well you did
with laying out
the second order criticism
paradigm so it's quite interesting to
read about and learn
yeah you know speaking of uh speaking of
a repository
you know at the very least you need a
language and a means of communication so
that you can convey
if i have an idea for new systems i need
to convey that to the rest of the world
in some way convey to you maybe you have
your own idea of what a
new system would look like so how do we
convey that idea how do we convey
a complicated idea to each other so that
we know what each other is talking about
and then we can start to do tests on
them or figure out which one works
better in what situations like
just just just just to begin we just
need a way to
communicate a way to present the
information so that we can understand
what each other is saying
just one kind of closing metaphor or at
least thought that comes to mind is like
let's say two people like a movie one
person said i love the special effects
the other one says the special effects
were super cheesy
i thought the story the other person
says i didn't even i don't like movies
but i like the book
so everyone can like the movie and the
point is they're aligned on action they
might even want to hang out together
they might be part of the fan club they
might
have a product related to the movie but
if the proj
if the problem is framed as okay come to
consensus on why you like this movie
we cannot personalize the solution
so everybody can have a different
understanding of why they like the movie
that's playing
out in front of our eyes and if it's
about
which part of this movie do you like or
not like
we're gonna be arguing a lot and if it's
like which movies should we watch
potentially that's a different question
or how should we reduce uncertainty
about the movie that we should watch
there's a lot of ways to frame it that i
would hope would be new
yeah i think so i think so yeah um
yeah maybe maybe we should leave it
there and we'll pick up more uh
next time and uh
looking forward john thanks so much uh
again
i'm gonna just re-upload this video in
case there's any weirdness with the live
stream so be high quality and just
uh we'll be in touch about planning
these upcoming sessions but
we will know that we will meet next week
on april 20th
at 3 p.m pacific pdt
for the third session of n
of bleep okay sounds good see you later
john
peace okay bye bye